so that you can live your life, and not the story that you've been telling yourself about your life. And that's how we walk around those bars. So I want to go back to the letter from the woman, about the affair. She asked me what she should do. Now, I have this word taped up in my office: ultracrepidarianism. The habit of giving advice or opinions outside of one's knowledge or competence. It's a great word, right? You can use it in all different contexts, I'm sure you will be using it after this TED Talk. I use it because it reminds me that as a therapist, I can help people to sort out what they want to do, but I can't make their life choices for them. Only you can write your story, and all you need are some tools. So what I want to do is I want to edit this woman's letter together, right here, as a way to show how we can all revise our stories. And I want to start by asking you to think of a story that you're telling yourself right now that might not be serving you well. It might be about a circumstance you're experiencing, it might be about a person in your life, it might even be about yourself. And I want you to look at the supporting characters. Who are the people who are helping you to uphold the wrong version of this story? For instance, if the woman who wrote me that letter told her friends what happened, they would probably offer her what's called "idiot compassion." Now, in idiot compassion, we go along with the story, we say, "You're right, that's so unfair," when a friend tells us that he didn't get the promotion he wanted, even though we know this has happened several times before because he doesn't really put in the effort, and he probably also steals office supplies. (Laughter) We say, "Yeah, you're right, he's a jerk," when a friend tells us that her boyfriend broke up with her, even though we know that there are certain ways she tends to behave in relationships, like the incessant texting or the going through his drawers, that tend to lead to this outcome. We see the problem, it's like, if a fight breaks out in every bar you're going to, it might be you. (Laughter) In order to be good editors, we need to offer wise compassion, not just to our friends, but to ourselves. This is what's called -- I think the technical term might be -- "delivering compassionate truth bombs." And these truth bombs are compassionate, because they help us to see what we've left out of the story. The truth is, we don't know if this woman's husband is having an affair, or why their sex life changed two years ago, or what those late-night phone calls are really about. And it might be that because of her history, she's writing a singular story of betrayal, but there's probably something else that she's not willing to let me, in her letter, or maybe even herself, to see. It's like that guy who's taking a Rorschach test. You all know what Rorschach tests are? A psychologist shows you some ink blots, they look like that, and asks, "What do you see?" So the guy looks at his ink blot and he says, "Well, I definitely don't see blood." And the examiner says, "Alright, tell me what else you definitely don't see." In writing, this is called point of view. What is the narrator not willing to see? So, I want to read you one more letter. And it goes like this. "Dear Therapist, I need help with my wife. Lately, everything I do irritates her, even small things, like the noise I make when I chew. At breakfast, I noticed that she even tries to secretly put extra milk in my granola so it won't be as crunchy." (Laughter) "I feel like she became critical of me after my father died two years ago. I was very close with him, and her father left when she was young, so she couldn't relate to what I was going through. There's a friend at work whose father died a few months ago, and who understands my grief. I wish I could talk to my wife like I talk to my friend, but I feel like she barely tolerates me now. How can I get my wife back?" OK. So, what you probably picked up on is that this is the same story I read you earlier, just told from another narrator's point of view. Her story was about a husband who's cheating, his story is about a wife who can't understand his grief. But what's remarkable, is that for all of their differences, what both of these stories are about is a longing for connection. And if we can get out of the first-person narration and write the story from another character's perspective, suddenly that other character becomes much more sympathetic, and the plot opens up. That's the hardest step in the editing process, but it's also where change begins. What would happen if you looked at your story and wrote it from another person's point of view? What would you see now from this wider perspective? That's why, when I see people who are depressed, I sometimes say, "You are not the best person to talk to you about you right now," because depression distorts our stories in a very particular way. It narrows our perspectives. The same is true when we feel lonely or hurt or rejected. We create all kinds of stories, distorted through a very narrow lens that we don't even know we're looking through. And then, we've effectively become our own fake-news broadcasters. I have a confession to make. I wrote the husband's version of the letter I read you. You have no idea how much time I spent debating between granola and pita chips, by the way. I wrote it based on all of the alternative narratives that I've seen over the years, not just in my therapy practice, but also in my column. When it's happened that two people involved in the same situation have written to me, unbeknownst to the other, and I have two versions of the same story sitting in my inbox. That really has happened. I don't know what the other version of this woman's letter is, but I do know this: she has to write it. Because with a courageous edit, she'll write a much more nuanced version of her letter that she wrote to me. Even if her husband is having an affair of any kind -- and maybe he is -- she doesn't need to know what the plot is yet. Because just by virtue of doing an edit, she'll have so many more possibilities for what the plot can become. Now, sometimes it happens that I see people who are really stuck, and they're really invested in their stuckness. We call them help-rejecting complainers. I'm sure you know people like this. They're the people who, when you try to offer them a suggestion, they reject it with, "Yeah, no, that will never work, because ..." "Yeah, no, that's impossible, because I can't do that." "Yeah, I really want more friends, but people are just so annoying." (Laughter) What they're really rejecting is an edit to their story of misery and stuckness. And so, with these people, I usually take a different approach. And what I do is I say something else. I say to them, "We're all going to die." I bet you're really glad I'm not your therapist right now. Because they look back at me the way you're looking back at me right now, with this look of utter confusion. But then I explain that there's a story that gets written about all of us, eventually. It's called an obituary. And I say that instead of being authors of our own unhappiness, we get to shape these stories while we're still alive. We get to be the hero and not the victim in our stories, we get to choose what goes on the page that lives in our minds and shapes our realities. I tell them that life is about deciding which stories to listen to and which ones need an edit. And that it's worth the effort to go through a revision because there's nothing more important to the quality of our lives than the stories we tell ourselves about them. I say that when it comes to the stories of our lives, we should be aiming for our own personal Pulitzer Prize. Now, most of us aren't help-rejecting complainers, or at least we don't believe we are. But it's a role that is so easy to slip into when we feel anxious or angry or vulnerable. So the next time you're struggling with something, remember, we're all going to die. (Laughter) And then pull out your editing tools and ask yourself: what do I want my story to be? And then, go write your masterpiece. Thank you. (Applause)
para que puedas vivir tu vida, y no la historia que te has contado sobre tu vida. Y así es como sorteamos esas rejas. Así que quiero volver a la carta de esa mujer, la de la infidelidad. Me preguntó que debería hacer. Tengo esta palabra anotada en mi oficina: "ultracrepidarianismo". La costumbre de dar consejos u opiniones que exceden nuestro saber y competencias. Gran palabra, ¿verdad? Se puede usar en cualquier contexto, Estoy segura de que la usarán tras esta charla TED, La uso porque me recuerda que, como sicoterapeuta, puedo ayudar a la gente a planear lo que quiere hacer, pero no puedo hacer sus elecciones vitales por ellos. Solo Uds. pueden escribir su propia historia y solo necesitan algunas herramientas. Así que, lo que quiero hacer es editar la carta de esta mujer, todos juntos, aquí y ahora, para poder mostrarles cómo revisar nuestras historias. Y quiero empezar pidiéndoles que piensen en una historia que se estén contando a Uds. ahora que quizás no les esté ayudando. Puede ser sobre una circunstancia que estén experimentando, sobre una persona de su vida, incluso sobre Uds. mismos. Y quiero que se fijen en los actores de reparto. ¿Qué personas les están ayudando a sostener la versión errada de esta historia? Por ejemplo, si la mujer que me escribió esta carta contara a sus amigos lo que pasaba, seguramente le ofrecerían lo que se llama "compasión idiota". En la compasión idiota -siguiendo con esta historia- diríamos: "Tienes razón, es horrible", cuando un amigo nos dice que no le dieron el ascenso que quería, aun cuando sabemos que ya le pasó varias veces porque realmente no se esforzó, y es probable que robara el material de oficina. (Risas) Decimos: "Tienes toda la razón, ese es un imbécil". Cuando una amiga nos dice que su novio la dejó, aun cuando sabemos que hay algunas cosas que hace normalmente con sus novios, como atiborrarlos de mensajes o rebuscar en sus cajones, que traen esas consecuencias. Vemos el problema, es como si cada vez que vas al bar hay siempre una pelea, quizás seas tú. (Risas) Para ser buenos editores, hay que ofrecer compasión sabia, no solo a nuestras amistades, sino a nosotros mismos. Esto se llama -creo que el término técnico sería- "Bombardeo compasivo de verdades". Y esas bombas de verdades son compasivas porque nos ayudan a ver lo que hemos obviado en nuestra historia. Lo cierto es que no sabemos si el marido está teniendo una aventura, o por qué su vida sexual cambió hace dos años, o qué son esas llamadas telefónicas que hace de madrugada. Y eso podría ser la razón de su historia, Ella habla de una historia de traición, pero es probable que haya algo más que no me dice en su carta, o quizás ella misma no lo ve. Es como ese tipo que hace el test de Rorschach. ¿Saben como son los test de Rorschach? Un sicólogo te enseña unas manchas de tinta parecidas a esto, y pregunta: "¿Qué ve Ud. aquí?" Entonces el tipo mira la mancha y dice: "Bueno, definitivamente, no veo sangre". Y el examinador dice: "Muy bien, dígame qué más no ve, definitavamente". En literatura, esto se llama "punto de vista". ¿Qué no quiere ver el narrador? Quiero leerles otra carta. Dice así: "Querida terapeuta, necesito que me ayude con mi mujer. Últimamente se enfada por todo, incluso por minucias, como el ruido que hago cuando mastico. En el desayuno he visto que le está echando más leche a mi granola para que no cruja tanto". (Risas) "Siento que es muy crítica conmigo desde que murió mi padre hace dos años. Él y yo estábamos muy unidos y su padre los dejó cuando era joven, así que no pudo entender por lo que pasaba. Tengo una amiga en el trabajo cuyo padre murió hace unos meses y que entiende mi pena. Me gustaría poder habla con mi esposa como hablo con mi amiga, pero creo que ya no me soporta. ¿Cómo puedo recuperar a mi mujer?". Muy bien. Supongo que ya han descubierto que es la misma historia que les he leído antes, justo desde el punto de vista de otro narrador. La historia de ella iba de un marido que la engañaba, la de él va de una esposa que no entiende su pena. Pero lo que llama la atención es que, con todas las diferencias que existen entre ambas historias, hay un deseo de acercarse. Y si pudiésemos ignorar al narrador en primera persona y escribir la historia desde la perspectiva de otro personaje, de repente este último se vuelve más empático y el argumento se abre. Este es el paso más duro en el proceso de editar pero también es de donde arranca el cambio. ¿Qué pasaría si vieses tu historia y la escribieras desde el punto de vista de otro? ¿Qué verías entonces desde una perspectiva más amplia? Por eso, cuando veo gente deprimida, a veces digo: "Justo ahora no eres la mejor persona con quien hablar de ti", ya que la depresión distorsiona nuestras historias especialmente. Reduce nuestra perspectiva. Sucede lo mismo cuando nos sentimos solos, heridos o rechazados. Creamos toda clase de historias, distorsionadas por una lente diminuta que nos impide saber qué estamos viendo. Y es cuando nos hacemos reemisores de nuestras propias noticias falsas. Debo confesarles algo. Yo escribí la versión del marido de la carta que les leí. No se imaginan cuánto tiempo invertí debatiendo entre granola y tostaditas, por cierto. La escribí basándome en todos los narradores alternativos que he visto en estos años, no solo como sicoterapeuta, sino también en mi columna. Cuando me ha pasado que dos personas viviendo la misma situación me han escrito, sin saber el uno del otro, y tengo dos versiones de la misma historia en mi bandeja de entrada. Me ha pasado de verdad. No sé cuál es la otra versión de la carta de esta mujer, pero sí sé esto: Ella tenía que escribirla. Porque con una edición valiente, ella escribirá una versión más aproximada de la que me escribió a mi. Incluso si su marido la está engañando -y quizás lo esté haciendo- ella no necesita saber de qué va el argumento. Porque solo por haberlo editado, ella tendrá más posibilidades de que el argumento cambie. Pero a veces sucede que veo gente atrapada de verdad, metida de verdad en su estancamiento. Se llaman "quejicas que rechazan ayuda". Seguro que conocen a gente así. Son los que, cuando les haces una sugerencia, la rechazan con un "bueno, no, eso no funcionará porque..." "Bueno, no, imposible, no puedo hacerlo". "Sí, quiero tener más amigos, pero la gente es insoportable". (Risas) Lo que realmente rechazan es la edición de su historia de miseria y estancamiento. Así que a estas personas me acerco de forma diferente. Y lo que hago es decirles algo más. Les digo: "Todos vamos a morir". Apuesto a que Uds. están contentos de no tenerme de sicóloga. Porque ellos me miran como Uds. me están mirando ahora absolutamente aturdidos. Pero entonces les explico que hay una historia que al final se escribe sobre todos nosotros. Se llama obituario. Y digo que en lugar de escribir nuestra propia infelicidad, debemos moldear esas historias mientras todavía vivimos. Tenemos que ser el héroe y no la víctima en nuestra historia, debemos elegir qué sucede en la página que vive en nuestra mente y forma nuestras realidades. Les digo que la vida se trata de decidir qué historias hay que escuchar y cuáles necesitan una edición. Y que vale la pena esforzarse por pasar por una revisión porque no hay nada más importante para la calidad de vida que las historias que nos contamos acerca de ellas. Les digo que cuando algo influye en la historia de nuestra vida, deberíamos optar a nuestro propio Premio Pulitzer personal. Pero la mayoría no somos quejicas que rechazan ayuda o, al menos, creemos que no lo somos. Pero es un rol en el que es muy fácil caer cuando estamos tensos, enfadados o indefensos. Así que la próxima vez que algo les agobie, recuerden: todos vamos a morir. (Risas) Echen mano a sus herramientas de edición y pregúntense: "¿Cómo quiero que sea mi historia? Y luego, escriban su obra maestra. Gracias. (Aplausos)